<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FeedFact.org</title>
    <link>http://feedfact.org/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on FeedFact.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 23:24:05 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://feedfact.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>little tweaks to ui and ux</title>
      <link>http://feedfact.org/post/little-tweaks-to-ui-and-ux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 23:24:05 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://feedfact.org/post/little-tweaks-to-ui-and-ux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There were a couple things i didn&amp;rsquo;t like that i wanted to fix&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix getting passed waiting for mouseover.  Ideally I would like the graph to show when you scroll&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it look a little better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one took a little bit, but i found a nice shortcut.  The text of the link matches the &amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo; of the article. Well, that is mostly true, Aparantly there are a bunch of articles that put a &amp;ldquo; | Author&amp;rdquo; at the end, or a &amp;ldquo; | publisher&amp;rdquo; at the end of their title in the Article.  But if that was the case then how did facebook actually get the real title? I bet they weren&amp;rsquo;t custom splitting on the &amp;ldquo;|&amp;rdquo;.  Then i found some extra meta tags that mostly worked as well. This required me switching the API to use a string for the Title, which also couldn&amp;rsquo;t even have the &amp;ldquo;|&amp;rdquo; otherwise that would break my API call for some reason. But in the end it now works pretty well.  Now, the overlay in the feed will be there as you scroll to it. which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does it look? well i decided to keep the same style as this site.  Pink on Black with white font.  Here is an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://feedfact.org/images/overlay3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overlay&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still lots to do, like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;updating the style of the Ranker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ranking within the feed, for things like videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;filters for your feed based on preferences in the chrome extensions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;oh and doing stuff to get people to use it&amp;hellip;. but maybe the screenshots can get more people excited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>exploring how this could work</title>
      <link>http://feedfact.org/post/exploring-how-this-could-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 18:43:03 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://feedfact.org/post/exploring-how-this-could-work/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Ok I devoted my entire weekend to get a prototype working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;this-was-the-plan&#34;&gt;This was the plan.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build an API that can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Receive POSTS to accept rankings of 5 dimensions for any article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return GET requests that take a url and return the aggregation of rankings for that url&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Get requests need to be quite performant and should be able to handle Caching, and user throttling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I do not want to manage any servers, this will all run without any servers (AWS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build a chrome extension that can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That can read your facebook news feed, and return the results for the article in your feed and overlay the aggregation of the results from the API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify when you are reading an article and allow an overlay for you to submit the ranking to the API while reading it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by exploring how to make a Chrome Extension.  Following some basic tutorials, I found out the chrome extensions are qutie awesome.  They are simple Javascript sites that have simple browser code that allows injecting Javascript on any page.  This was perfect, just what i needed, the next thing i needed was to be able to get the URLS out of the page.  This was not so easy.  When facebook loads the news feed page the anchor tags did not contain the urls of the article.  And even after using hacky techniques like setInterval, the url still wouldnt be populated.  It was only right after when a user mouses over the article in the feed did the url get populated. From that point, I was able to make an overlay. Its not the nicest thing in the world. But the point is that it was doable.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://feedfact.org/images/overlay.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overlay&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool so the UI can work in the facebook feed.  However, it means that everytime a user mouseovers an article in the facebook news i need to fire a call to the API, and render quite quickly. Noted.  Ok, onto the API&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I basically did everything with Amazon Web Services.  It took a while getting everything wired together.  Route53, for getting my domain name and DNS; Amazone API Gateway for generating tokens, throttling and caching; Amazon Lambda to take the request and do some simple math logic; DynamoDB for storing all data; Oh and S3 for storing and hosting this site.  Connecting these things was not that easy, one of the things that caught me was getting SSL certificates right.  Majority of the weekend was devoted to configuring and tweaking my lambda function. Which does some cool iterative standard deviation calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok with the facebook news feed overlay, and the API, I needed to get the article submissions working.  In order to get this to work the chrome extension needed to find a way to determine whether the page being viewed was an article or not.  Fortunately I was able to find a way using the meta tags in the page that (mostly) works. I then use a some simple js sliders for the form, and tada.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://feedfact.org/images/overlay2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overlay&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does work with a couple little bugs i need to fix.  It was exhausting.  And well worth it.  After some bug fixing, Some test users. and i think we have something.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>what&#39;s this all about</title>
      <link>http://feedfact.org/info/whats-this-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 17:53:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://feedfact.org/info/whats-this-all-about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to make tag lines for this project.  You know those one-liners that simplify topics of great complexity into something that can be used as a replacement for the idea.  I could use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Transforming clickbait to journalism&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Journalism for the people not for publishers&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;It&#39;s time to take out trash&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m not concerned about nailing the perfect one-liner to understand the project.  What I am concerned about is nailing the problem and how this solution could be used for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own lines they draw in the sand.  And when that line is crossed they take action.  Everyone has different thresholds for what it takes for their lines to be crossed.  People who tend to talk in binaries, i.e. &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re with us or against us&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Conservative or Liberal&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Black or White&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;; These people tend to have very low thresholds, and have a very simple delineation between when action should be taken or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is if you are a person that has grown up appreciating nuance, can respect other view points, make attempts to walk in other peoples shoes and get fulfillment out of it; Then you probably have a line that is harder to cross.  Why? because you are comfortable being wrong. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a strength.  You have learned that the rightness and wrongness is rarely a binary, but more of a scale that can only be understood well after the time of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so what? Well here is where it gets worse.  The political lines that are being crossed that normally would motivate people to action are getting muddled by publishers.  Each publisher has one motivation.  Generate money.  They may say they have an obligation to an ideal of the truth, but the only way they can stay relevant is by having great one-liners.  Catchy, brilliant one-liners that shock, or make you laugh.  If they have done that well, then you go read it, and the publisher can sell more ads.  What becomes alarming is that they fuel the fire of people that tend to be more binary and the rest is left sifting through garbage. And now as each publisher needs to compete with each other, the one-liners are getting more and more polarizing. Making the lines of the binaries crossed no matter what side you are on.  And the publishers are getting better at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is left over is a wasteland of journalism that anyone can say &amp;ldquo;Oh I don&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rdquo; even if the article actually has some fact behind it.  The funnier part is that both sides agree on this issue and conveniently are using it only when it disagrees with their opinion.  So when a line is crossed from one side, the other will complain, &amp;ldquo;Oh they were fed false information.&amp;rdquo;  Rather than having the important discussion of answering, &amp;ldquo;What is the reason for those people disagreeing with me?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best value of journalism comes when it can actually &lt;strong&gt;change&lt;/strong&gt; your mind. But that can&amp;rsquo;t happen when it&amp;rsquo;s mainly focused on polarizing people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;solution-well-a-potential-one&#34;&gt;Solution (well, a potential one&amp;hellip;)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok its not all doom and gloom. I think there is some value in looking through the polarized content to get a pulse on a situation, and then filter through the facts to get a sense of what is going on.  It&amp;rsquo;s not impossible to get the details out of the news coverage (yet).  There are attempts at trying to solve the problem but the wrong people are trying to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution can&amp;rsquo;t come from publishers because they have an inherit bias.  The basis of any solution needs to emphasize one important thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Trust&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why it needs to come from people like you and I.  Not Artificial Intelligence. Not Facebook. Not A Government Agency.  Not a company with unkown board members.  It needs to come from us.  The people who are comfortable with nuance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my way of helping is getting the right news junkies together.  Whose motivation is closer to understanding an issue, rather than being a spokesperson for a political side.  These people I will give access to an API where they can rate articles and everyone in the world can consume those ratings right in any news feed they wish (and yes even in your Facebook news).  This is not a scheme to make anyone rich.  I am not going to resell this data to anyone. I am not going to publish any individuals viewpoint.  The point is that if an article is credible, it will be clear as day that it is.  And anyone will be able to apply any filters on content in your feed. If you want to just look at trash, you can do that.  If you want to only look at articles that have been reviewed by this team you can do that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to deter the polarization of the media, by giving anyone access to credible assessments to articles right in the places they see them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>thoughts from experts</title>
      <link>http://feedfact.org/post/thoughts-from-experts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 17:38:31 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://feedfact.org/post/thoughts-from-experts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There have been three different experts whom I have talked to in depth about this project.  The first person is someone who has set up multiple different companies.  He has been able to generate funding and actualized on many different products and projects.  I received a lot of great feedback about how to structure a deck, and how to go about getting everything ready to start getting money for this idea.  There was a lot of conversation over whether or not I go the non-profit vs. for-profit route, and whether their is a viable business model in here that would generate investor interest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next person I talked to is an expert on Reputation Systems.  This is not as simple as looking a distributions and removing outliers.  There are a lot of things to be concerned with what I like to call “Strategic Voting” but the main idea is that the algorithm/process needs to be able to stop collusion while still being timely.  This balance is the main engineering challenge of the project, and why it is not as simple as a weekend hack job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last person was a professional journalism with ties to different news organizations.  Our talk covered mainly how these organizations functioned, and how best to get the “Trust” that was missing in news articles.  I found out about the Knight Foundation whose organization is focused on grants for initiatives similar to mine, and she suggested that this project might be an ideal candidate for these grants.  It is sounding like the main route might be to pursue connecting with non-affiliated journalists, and journalism schools to get their rankings of articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was consistently stated was that each expert agrees with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This solution cannot be accomplished by a big company or media entity (like facebook), because the main problem it addresses is “Trust” and each of those organizations have to start with an inherent bias because they are all publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The time to act is now, or preferably like six months ago.  The issue this project addresses is frequently being dealt with by everyone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the questions I need to answer in order to get moving:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the fastest route to getting the ball rolling?:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an alpha product that accepts ranking and provides basic stats, and leverage my social network to get those rankings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a deck to get the money, and connections needed to get the right people to rank&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply to the Knight Foundation to get a grant/connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should the organization be setup?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Individual) to get to poc, then take care of legal entity later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Non-profit) Benefit of looking more Altruistic to help with “Trust”, however the Bureaucratic hurdles might be take too long to get going&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Com) Might have a slight hit to “Trust”, but if the investment dollars are well taken care of, and board is carefully chosen might not be a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is exactly the mission Statement?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it building “trust” in the news?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it rewarding good journalism?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it early identification of bad journalism?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it about getting positive reinforcement back to publishers for good articles?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do i want to get people involved?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do i keep this a secret to those i trust?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do i start getting people excited now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do i find the right people?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>